Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Ongoing Career, 1993; XVII.
  - Professional and Civic Work, 5.
    - New Material Added, May 2017
      - Center for Strategic and International Studies, 2001
        - Background for special session re the need for national strategy for production of vaccines, etc. to meet bio warfare threats to U.S. citizens, November 1, 2001 (Box 1047, Folder 17)
        - CSIS Biotechnology & Public Policy Initiative Overview, November 11, 2001 (Box 1047, Folder 18)
        - Meeting: National Strategy for Bio Threat Vaccines, Therapeutics, and Diagnostics, November 16, 2001 (Box 1047, Folder 19)
      - Elan Pharmaceuticals, LP, 1996-2006
        Elan was a drug delivery systems manufacturer in Ireland, whose research areas coincided with the Thornburgh's' interests in disability. After several years of participation on its Board, financial problems ensued and Thornburgh after helping with replacing top management left the Board and ceased interaction.
        - Thornburgh elected to Board of Directors, March 14, 1996 (Box 1047, Folder 20)
        - Event and news articles, April-May 1997 (Box 1047, Folder 21)
        - Articles and meeting, May-September 1997 (Box 1047, Folder 22)
        - Elan Annual Report, 1997 (Box 1047, Folder 23)
        - Meeting and minutes, December 5, 1997 (Box 1047, Folder 24)
        - Board Meeting, Dublin, January 27-29, 1998 (Box 1047, Folder 25)
        - Correspondence, articles, February-May, 1998 (Box 1047, Folder 26)
        - Minutes, agendas and meetings of Board, January-April, 1998 (Box 1047, Folder 27)
        - "Project Festival: Acquisition Proposal", April 17, 1998 (Box 1047, Folder 28)
        - "Presentation for the Board of Directors" re Project Nirvana, April 24, 1998 (Box 1047, Folder 29)
        - Board Meeting, Athlone, Ireland, June 26, 1998 (Box 1047, Folder 30)
        - Board Meeting, August 18, 1998 (Box 1047, Folder 31)
        - Board Meeting, September 11, 1998 (Box 1048, Folder 1)
        - Board Meeting, New York, December 5, 1998 (Box 1048, Folder 2)
        - Board Meeting, Dublin, February 26, 1999 (Box 1048, Folder 3)
        - News release and articles, January 1999 (Box 1048, Folder 4)
        - Board Meeting, Dublin, February 25, 1999 (Box 1048, Folder 5)
        - Articles, May - September 1999 (Box 1048, Folder 6)
        - Financial Review, 2000 (Box 1048, Folder 7)
        - Elan on "The List" Forbes Magazine, January 8, 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 8)
        - Board Meeting, Ireland, March 2, 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 9)
        - Articles, March-May 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 10)
        - Financial Review Quarter 1, 2001, April 23, 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 11)
        - Board Meeting, scheduled events, May 31, 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 12)
        - Meeting Organization & Compensation Committee, May 31, 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 13)
        - Articles, June - November 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 14)
        - Board Meeting, Dublin, December 7, 2001 (Box 1048, Folder 15)
        - Board Meeting, Dublin, March 1, 2002 (Box 1048, Folder 16)
        - News articles and Correspondence, May-December 2002 (Box 1048, Folder 17)
        - News articles, January 1-6, 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 18)
        - News articles, January 10-31, 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 19)
        - News articles, February 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 20)
        - Elan Amended Corporate Guidelines, November 28, 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 21)
        - Compliance Steering Committee Reports, November 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 22)
        - Board of Directors Investment Review, December 5, 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 23)
        - Board of Directors Meeting Materials, December 4-5, 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 24)
        - Board of Directors Meeting (part 1), March 20, 2005 (Box 1048, Folder 25)
        - Board of Directors Meeting (part 2), March 20, 2005 (Box 1048, Folder 26)
        - Elan Core Business, March 20, 2005 (Box 1048, Folder 27)
        - Elan Core Business, March 20, 2005 (Box 1048, Folder 28)
        - Elan Core Business, March 20, 2005 (Box 1048, Folder 29)
        - Elan Core Business, March 20, 2005 (Box 1048, Folder 30)
        - Elan Securities Exchange Art proceedings, July 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 31)
        - Elan News articles, March 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 32)
        - Elan News articles, October-December 2003 (Box 1048, Folder 33)
        - Correspondence and articles, 2005 (Box 1048, Folder 34)
        - Elan: California Law Case, August 2006 (Box 1048, Folder 35)
      - Disability Rights Treaty, 2013-2014
        Thornburgh's long standing support of persons with disabilities has led to his continued effort to encourage and support the U.S. passage of the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (CRPD), that would promote disability rights worldwide.
        - Op-Ed Philadelphia Inquirer: "Ratify Convention to break down global barriers for the disabled: Thornburgh and Ridge & previous testimony, December 1, 2013 (Box 1048, Folder 36)
        - Radio interviews: withdrawal of support by Senator Corker, January 2014 (Box 1048, Folder 37)
        - Notes re radio interviews re the disability treaty, February-March, 2014 (Box 1048, Folder 38)
        - Talking Points & calls: Bond v. US, case re US treaty enforcement, May - June, 2014 (Box 1048, Folder 39)
      - Legal Services Task Force, 2013-2014
        Thornburgh continued his association with LSC for many years. Equal Justice under Law was an issue to which Thornburgh was long committed and continued into 2013.
        - Updated recommendations of LSC's Pro Bono Task Force, March 2013 (Box 1048, Folder 40)
        - Issue: "Do our Ethics Rules Access to Justice, May 2013 (Box 1048, Folder 41)
        - Neighborhood Legal Services Association correspondence, October 2013 (Box 1048, Folder 42)
        - Pro Bono Awards Reception, Pittsburgh, Thornburgh participant, October 2013 (Box 1048, Folder 43)
      - Civil Justice Reform, Tort Reform, 1995-2005
        Thornburgh's interest in this subject derived in part from his participation while Attorney General in the Council on Competitiveness report (available here): Agenda for Civil Justice Reform in America, August 1991. Several widely publicized cases revived public interest in problems associated with lawsuit abuse. Thornburgh made many appearances on behalf of Civil Justice Reform Groups in the next several years. A number of states enacted tort reform, including Ohio and California where Thornburgh had put major effort for the Civil Justice Reform Group. As Chairman of the Washington Legal Foundation Policy Board there was additional support of tort reform for years ongoing.
        - Correspondence, articles, and Radio Media event, 1995 (Box 1050, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence, articles, publications, 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 2)
        - California Tour, December 5-8, 1995 (Box 1050, Folder 3)
        - Civil Justice Reform efforts in Ohio: Hardy v. GM, December 1995-January 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 4)
        - Civil Justice Reform/Senate Vote: Radio Programs around country, March 19, 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 5)
        - Civil Justice Reform/Bill of Rights; Arizona Radio Media Tour, March 27, 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 6)
        - Communications regarding Corporate Counsel Briefing in May, January-May 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 7)
        - Working Papers: Corporate Counsel Briefing, May, 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 8)
        - Corporate Counsel Briefing: Civil Justice Reform Panel, May 21, 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 9)
        - "Civil Justice and the Litigation Process…", September 12-13, 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 10)
        - "Civil Justice Reform: What Now?" Booklet, October 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 11)
        - Correspondence and potential op-eds & articles, April-November 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 12)
        - Correspondence, February, October 1996 (Box 1050, Folder 13)
        - Correspondence, articles, Thornburgh publications, 1997 (Box 1050, Folder 14)
        - Meetings, articles, correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 1050, Folder 15)
        - Correspondence, articles, 2000-2001 (Box 1050, Folder 16)
        - Correspondence, articles, 2002 (Box 1050, Folder 17)
        - Correspondence, articles, and remarks, 2003 (Box 1050, Folder 18)
        - Articles, publications, award, 2004 (Box 1050, Folder 19)
        - Articles, correspondence, 2005 (Box 1050, Folder 20)
      - Electronic Voting (e-voting)
        In July 2004 Thornburgh Co-Chaired a study by the National Academy of Science on electronic voting. This initial meeting included persons with diverse views and expertise, including computer scientists and information technologists, political scientists, and others. Subsequently a smaller group of persons specifically interested were gathered by Thornburgh. Committee: A Framework for Understanding Electronic Voting. Ultimately an Op-Ed was published and a valuable reports were distributed May and July 2006.
        - Articles about e-mailing votes and e-voting, 2004 (Box 1050, Folder 21)
        - Final Agenda: A Framework for Understanding Electronic Voting Meeting, December 9-10, 2004 (Box 1050, Folder 22)
        - Index of background materials for the meeting, December 2004 (Box 1050, Folder 23)
        - Report of the Commission on Federal Election Reform: Building Confidence in U.S. Elections, September 2005 (Box 1050, Folder 24)
        - "Preparing for Electronic Voting in the November 2006 Elections, " meeting Agenda, related articles, attendees, May 12-13, 2006 (Box 1050, Folder 25)
        - Notes from meeting, May 13, 2006 (Box 1050, Folder 26)
        - Transcript from meeting, May 30, 2006 (Box 1050, Folder 27)
        - Correspondence regarding committee meeting & press release, June - July, 2006 (Box 1050, Folder 28)
        - News articles re e-voting, 2006-2008 (Box 1050, Folder 29)
        - Thornburgh/Celeste Op-Ed: "Watch Out for Voting Day Bugs" Washington Post, August 28, 2006 (Box 1050, Folder 30)
      - National Museum of Industrial History, 1999-2008
        Thornburgh served on the original Board of Directors of the National Museum of Industrial History, beginning January 1999. The Museum is affiliated with the Smithsonian Institution and is viewed as the premier museum of industrial history in the U.S. It is dedicated to preserving the story and accomplishments of American industry and is our country's largest brownfield project, on the site of the former Bethlehem Steel corporation plant, in Bethlehem, PA. After some funding and leadership delays it is scheduled to open Summer 2016.
        - Thornburgh to serve on Board of Trustees, and related articles, January 1999 (Box 1051, Folder 1)
        - Corporate Fact sheet, background materials and plans, April 7, 1999 (Box 1051, Folder 2)
        - Project Review Meeting, Business Plans and Fundraising plans, April 7,1999 (Box 1051, Folder 3)
        - Newspaper articles about the Bethlehem Works, June-December, 1999 (Box 1051, Folder 4)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, December 16, 1999 (Box 1051, Folder 5)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, July 14, 2000 (Box 1051, Folder 6)
        - National Museum Funding Proposal, Summer 2000 (Box 1051, Folder 7)
        - National Museum "Proposed Museum Operations 2005", June 2000 (Box 1051, Folder 8)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, March 9, 2001 (Box 1051, Folder 9)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, November 9, 2001 (Box 1051, Folder 10)
        - Board of Directors telephone meeting, December 20, 2000 (Box 1051, Folder 11)
        - "WIRED" magazine articles re "Bethlehem: Field of Dreams", February 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 13)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, April 3, 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 14)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, May 15, 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 15)
        - Correspondence, February-March 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 12)
        - National Museum "Preview Center", Spring/Summer 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 16)
        - National Museum "Phase #2", Summer 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 17)
        - Correspondence and Articles, May-June 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 18)
        - Board of Directors Meeting and news articles, July 17, 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 19)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, September 18, 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 20)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, November 21, 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 21)
        - Board of Directors Meeting (cancelled), December, 2002 (Box 1051, Folder 22)
        - Correspondence, April-May 2006 (Box 1051, Folder 23)
        - Board of Directors Meeting Agenda, September 28, 2006 (Box 1051, Folder 24)
        - Updated reference binder, Board of Directors, October 18, 2006 (Box 1051, Folder 25)
        - Campaign and Progress Reports, November-December 2006 (Box 1051, Folder 26)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, December 7, 2006 (Box 1051, Folder 27)
        - Board of Directors Meeting and fund-raising documents, March 8, 2007 (Box 1051, Folder 28)
        - Donor prospects and status, April-May 2007 (Box 1051, Folder 29)
        - Board of Directors Meeting and Campaign Progress Report, June 14, 2007 (Box 1051, Folder 30)
        - Donor prospects and status, July-August, 2007 (Box 1051, Folder 31)
        - Board of Directors Meeting and Campaign Progress, September 13, 2007 (Box 1051, Folder 32)
        - Donor prospects and events, October-November, 2007 (Box 1051, Folder 33)
        - Board of Directors Meeting and presentations, December 20, 2007 (Box 1051, Folder 34)
        - Fund raising status and correspondence, January - February 2008 (Box 1051, Folder 35)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, March 13, 2008 (Box 1051, Folder 36)
        - Board updates and information, April 2008 (Box 1051, Folder 37)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, May 29, 2008 (Box 1051, Folder 38)
        - Talking Points and Mission documents, June-July 2008 (Box 1051, Folder 39)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, September 11, 2008 (Box 1051, Folder 40)
        - Board of Directors Meeting, December 11, 2008 (Box 1051, Folder 41)
      - NASAA Task Force on Securities Regulation
        In October 1995 Thornburgh was asked to be a member of a "distinguished blue-ribbon panel of experts," the "latest phase in a long-term regulatory review process initiated by North American Securities Administrators Association (NASAA). The goal was to undertake "a full, uncensored and deliberate debate that takes into account all important perspectives relevant to the shared areas of state and federal securities regulation." A final report was to be presented to NASAA's Spring Conference in April 1996.
        - North American Securities Administrators Association (NASAA) announcement re. "distinguished blue-ribbon panel" and related information, October 1995 (Box 1052, Folder 1)
        - First Meeting of panel: background information and agenda, etc., November 29, 1995 (Box 1052, Folder 2)
        - Extensive information about state regulation of mutual funds, January 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 3)
        - Meeting agenda, notes, discussion papers, January 18, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 4)
        - Meeting materials, January 18, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 5)
        - Meeting materials, January 18, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 6)
        - Next meeting agenda and notes, February 28-29, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 7)
        - Meeting information and notes, February 28-29, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 8)
        - Meeting information and notes, February 28-29, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence and notes, January-March, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 10)
        - Meeting agenda, notes, discussion papers, March 25-26, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 11)
        - Panel discussion: future of federal-state mutual regulation, April 9, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 12)
        - Agenda: NASAA Task Force Meeting, May 22, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 13)
        - Agenda and documents Task Force Meeting, June 27, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 14)
        - Final Report Language, July 25, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 15)
        - Review of Task Force Final Report, July 30, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 16)
        - Draft Part B: Registration of Securities, undated (Box 1052, Folder 17)
        - Draft Part B: Registration of Securities, undated (Box 1052, Folder 18)
        - Task Force Meeting, July 31, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 19)
        - NASAA 1996 Annual Conference, September 8-10, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 20)
        - Pre meeting notes and Draft Mission Statement Preamble, September 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 21)
        - Reorganized and revised draft of Task Force Report, November 13, 1996 (Box 1052, Folder 22)
        - "Report of the Task Force on the Future of Shared State and Federal Securities Regulation, October 1997 (Box 1052, Folder 23)
      - NAPA Panel on Economic Development, 1995-1996
        The Economic Development Administration (ADA) of Department of Commerce in 1995 asked NAPA (National Academy of Public Administration) to review the federal role in promoting economic development and make recommendations about its mission, strategies and organization. NAPA convened a distinguished panel, Richard Thornburgh Chair, to offer concrete suggestions and establish a framework for on-going discussion of the roles and responsibilities of the private sector and government at all levels.
        - NAPA Economic Development Project first committee meeting and subsequent Panel Membership list, August 9, 1995 (Box 1053, Folder 1)
        - Background Paper: "Who Is Responsible For Economic Development", September 19,1995 (Box 1053, Folder 2)
        - Research Paper: "National, Regional, and Local Economic Development Policy: New Thinking About Old Ideas", August 18, 1995 (Box 1053, Folder 3)
        - Background Papers for upcoming panel meeting, November 1995 (Box 1053, Folder 4)
        - Meeting Agenda, Thornburgh notes, draft discussion paper, work plan, and panel members and bios, December 4, 1995 (Box 1053, Folder 5)
        - Meeting issue papers and background, December 4, 1995 (Box 1053, Folder 6)
        - Background notes, preliminary agenda, project overview paper, January 16-17, 1996 (Box 1053, Folder 7)
        - Notes and results first panel meeting, December 4, 1995 (Box 1053, Folder 8)
        - Panel meeting notes and agenda, February 26, 1996 (Box 1053, Folder 9)
        - NAPA Fall Meeting: "Improving Government in the New Term", November 14-16, 1996 (Box 1053, Folder 10)
        - NAPA Conference on report: A Path to Smarter Economic Development: Reassessing the Federal Role" a one-year study, November 22-23, 1996 (Box 1053, Folder 11)
      - NAPA: Thornburgh Member Board of Trustees
        NAPA's History began February 1967. It from the start has had a significant impact on government institutions and public administration. It has advised regarding relationship of federal, state, regional and local governments, thus increasing understanding of requirements and opportunities for sound governance.
        - Publication: The First 25 Years: 1867-1992, April 1997 (Box 1053, Folder 12)
        - Board of Trustees Meeting, October 1997 (Box 1053, Folder 13)
        - Board of Trustees Retreat, January 30-31, 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 14)
        - Board of Trustees Retreat, January 30-31, 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 15)
        - Board of Trustees Retreat, January 30-31, 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 16)
        - Board of Trustees Fall Meeting, November 19-21, 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 17)
        - Board of Trustees Fall Meeting, November 19-21 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 18)
        - Board of Trustees Fall Meeting, November 19-21, 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 19)
        - Webb Lecture to Trustees Meeting (as delivered and copies), November 20, 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 20)
        - Complimentary correspondence re Web Lecture, November-December 1998 (Box 1053, Folder 21)
        - Board of Trustees Fall Meeting, November 18-20, 1999 (Box 1053, Folder 22)
        - Board of Trustees Fall Meeting, November 18-20, 1999 (Box 1053, Folder 23)
        - Board of Trustees Fall Meeting, November 18-20, 1999 (Box 1053, Folder 24)
        - Correspondence and Reports, December 1999 (Box 1053, Folder 25)
        - Survey of Key Issues Biographical information, 1999 (Box 1053, Folder 26)
        - Correspondence and Reports, January 2000 (Box 1053, Folder 27)
        - Board of Trustees Retreat, February 2000 (Box 1053, Folder 28)
        - Board of Trustees Retreat, February 2000 (Box 1053, Folder 29)
        - Board of Trustees Retreat, February 2000 (Box 1053, Folder 30)
      - NAPA: Chair, Independent NASA Security Review Panel, 2013-2014
        In August 2013 Thornburgh agreed to Chair the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's (NASA) panel for NAPA, an independent security review.
        - Panel members, "Role of Panel," "Foreign National Access Management Draft Plan," panel history, August 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 1)
        - Preliminary information to forthcoming meeting, July-August 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 2)
        - Academy Foreign National Access Management Panel Meeting & Goddard Center visit, August 23, 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 3)
        - Second panel meeting, September 26, 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 4)
        - Comprehensive overview of NASA pre second panel meeting, September 20, 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 5)
        - NASA Third Panel Meeting, October 30, 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 6)
        - Third Panel Meeting, November 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 7)
        - Panel's "First Deliverable: Initial List of Findings and Recommendations, December 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 8)
        - NASA "Agency Risk Management Procedural Requirements" Effective Date: December 16, 2013; Expiration: December 16, 2013, December 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 9)
        - Draft Final Report: Review of Foreign National Access Management, January 6, 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 10)
        - Final Report: NASA Independent Review of Foreign National Access Management, January 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 11)
        - Panel meeting with NASA, February 4, 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 12)
        - Correspondence and positive statements re Final Report, February 7-12, 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 13)
        - Drafts and final Written statement by Thornburgh, Panel Chair, for House Committee on Appropriations, Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, Science and Related Agencies, April 8, 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 14)
        - NASA response to NAPA Independent Review, January 2014, March-April 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 15)
        - Drafts and final as delivered Oral Statement by Thornburgh, Panel Chair, Before House Committee on Appropriations, Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, Science and Related Agencies, April 8, 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 16)
        - Statement of The Honorable Charles F. Bolden, Jr. Administrator NASA, before Subcommittee, April 8, 2014 (Box 1054, Folder 17)
        - Newspaper articles re space exploration, August-December 2013 (Box 1054, Folder 18)
  - Media Interviews and Background Information, 6.
    During the years following Thornburgh's work at the United Nations, he "embarked upon a new mini-career as a television 'personality'" (Evidence, p.352). Thornburgh, of course, as a political figure, had much experience appearing as guest on network news shows, but the 1990s explosion of twenty-four-hour-a-day news networks, such as FOX News, CNN, CNBC, etc., drastically increased the news shows and their coverage.